It is nice to meet you, Sunim.
(Sunim) Yes.
I have two questions to ask. The first
is that I can't focus when I'm praying.
Although I try to give it my full
attention during my prayers,
I instead think of things like
what happened yesterday
or what is on sale at
the department store.
It seems to get better
little bit at a time,
but I can't always stay focused.
Some Sunim have said that you are focused
when you can hear your tone
while reciting your prayers.
So I've tried it, but it
doesn't seem to work.
So I am wondering whether
there is a method to concentrating.
My second question is this.
I read from your book
that I should be the accommodating person
when in conflict with another person.
But the thought that follows is,
"Why do I always have to be
the one who accommodates?"
Whenever I have conflicts with my
husband, children, in laws or siblings,
I keep thinking of why I am
the only one who is trying.
These are my questions for you today.
Let's start with the later.
The reason why you should be accommodating
is because this benefits yourself.
If you understand the other person,
then your heart is at peace,
but, if you don't, then
your heart is uneasy.
You are being understanding
to benefit yourself
and not really to benefit
the other person.
It's to ease your own mind.
When you hate someone,
you are the one who suffer,
and, when you understand the other
person, you are the one at peace.
It is for your own benefit.
If you're thinking, "Why do I need to be
only one?", then stop being accommodating.
You will just suffer for it.
I'm not saying that you'll go to
heaven or receive blessings
if you think a certain way.
I'm explaining the principles
of how things work.
If you think a certain way,
it will be more beneficial for you.
The reason why most people
suffer is that they insist only
on their perspective and insist
on changing others.
That makes life exhausting.
People think that their
problem is a huge deal,
but what do you think
when you hear others' problems?
It is just one of the stories
among countless others.
Many people invest in stocks
or real estate these days.
Do all of them make a profit?
Or do some make money
while others do not?
There are those who would profit
and those who would lose money.
It is expected to lose some money
when you are trying to make money.
Also, when the colleges are only
accepting half a million people
out of 1 million applicants,
doesn't half of the applicant
have to get rejected?
They have to get rejected.
There's no other way around it.
It may be a huge deal
for the rejected applicants,
but it's not a big deal
for the rest of us.
It's an election year,
and some will win and others will lose
It's a big deal for the candidates,
but it isn't for the rest of us.
Losing an election isn't a life
or death issue to us.
Like so, things look serious
when you are focused on yourself,
but it really isn't if you
simply look at the issue.
If you are wrapped up in yourself,
things become a huge deal.
But, if you understand the other person's
perspective and look at the big picture,
you can be at peace in any situation.
If you are self-absorbed and stubborn,
small things become huge deals,
and that creates stresses for you.
That's why you should be understanding.
But you don't have to if you don't want to.
In other words, you shouldn't be understanding
to your husband because it helps him.
You should be understanding
because it helps you.
What else can you do when your
husband is already that way?
When I was in the US, someone
asked me this question.
She asked me, "Sunim, why do you
tell only women to be repentant?"
"Shouldn't men repent as well?"
(Sunim) "Men should, too."
(Questioner) "Then, please,
tell men to repent as well."
So I said, "Men, please, be repentant."
But did that change anything?
I asked her,
"I have a mother, too, so
why would I side with men?"
She told me, "Because
you are a man as well."
So I replied, "My mother is a woman,
so I am on women's side."
I am always on the side of the person
who asked me the question.
If a man asks me what he can do
with a wife who is too difficult,
there are only two choices.
Either he says goodbye
or he adapts to his wife.
There's no other alternative.
(Q) "Couldn't I change her instead?"
(Sunim) Give it a try.
If it was possible, why would
he come and ask me?
He is asking because he
couldn't change his wife.
We need to give up on the idea
that we can change other people.
It's hard enough to change yourself;
then, how can we expect to change others?
It's not that easy.
It's easier to change the world than for the husband to change the wife or wife to change the husband.
It's easier to change the world
than for the husband to change
the wife or wife to change the husband.
So I do that for them instead.
I change the wife for her husband,
I change the husband for his wife,
and I change the
parents for their children.
You listen to me when I tell you things,
but you never listen when your own
husband is trying to tell you things.
Likewise, your husband
won't listen to you either.
You may ask me to change them for you,
but I don't do such favors.
I tell you to change your thoughts
and widen your perspective
for your own good.
And what was your first question?
That's right; you can't focus.
It's not just you with that problem
but everyone else here.
In their heads, their thoughts are
going from shopping to out of space.
They think about their childhood,
about out of space, a book,
a movie, past loves,
and back and forth like this.
This is okay. It's not a problem.
When this happens, think to yourself,
"Ah, these are the anguishes within me.
You don't notice this in your daily life,
but, even now, your thoughts
are going back and forth.
You're not aware of
this video in your head
because the live video here is too strong.
If you close your eyes and
ears and turn off the live video,
your own video starts playing.
Foremost, know that you
have these anguishes.
Don't think that you need to be rid of them
or wonder why you are having these thoughts.
What is your current prayer?
What is most important for me right
now is my child's college entrance exam.
So do you pray?
"Please, let my child
do well on the exam?"
I pray that I can become good enough
to change my child's rough personality.
You're having distractions
because you're praying so foolishly.
Isn't your child's psyche more
apprehensive than yours?
Who is more anxious, you or your child?
(Questioner) My child.
Yes.
So you should pray, "I will
understand my child's heart."
In doing so, you will
understand your child
even when he is goofing
off or acting anxious.
"Yes, yes, you can act this way."
Like so, you can help
him in his anxiousness.
You may yell at him, "Why are you
watching TV when your exam is coming up?"
But your child is watching
TV because he is nervous.
Do you understand?
If you understand him,
you can wait for him and say,
"Studying is hard, isn't it?
Let me cook something for you?"
You can start a conversation
like this and then tell him,
"I know it's hard,
but you have to do what you can
since you can't give up
now with only few days left."
If you talk like this, he
will go back to studying.
If you instead yell, "What are you doing
when the exam is only a few days away?
I'm praying this hard for you,
and you're doing this?"
This may have him go back to his room,
but would he feel good or bad?
Since he'd feel awful, he'd
lock his door and go to sleep.
So this wouldn't help at all.
So you should pray, "I will
understand my child's heart."
Even if he failed his exam,
since you understand him
through your prayers,
you will be able to think,"It's okay;
there's always next year."
And you won't feel upset.
Okay. I will understand my child.
I will change myself.
Don't say you'll change yourself.
I think it was hard because I have only
been praying that everything is alright.
So pray to understand your child.
Next, pray in repentance to your husband.
When you say your child
has a rough personality,
it is because you have
a rough personality.
Praying to subdue yourself
is not the answer.
If you lower yourself to your husband,
you naturally become softer.
Since this already transferred to your
child, don't pray to change yourself.
Instead, pray, "I'm sorry, dear,
for putting myself before you."
"I repent."
If you pray in repentance like this
you can recall many things
that you should repent on.
When you are praying
to understand your child,
you recall all the times you
didn't understand him.
You would think,"Oh, I faltered again.
How he must dread studying…
Instead I yelled at him for watching TV."
Or, "Oh, I argued again
when all I had to do was
to agree with my husband."
When you repent like this,
there is little room for distractions.
Try praying like this.